<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter ballancing the necessity of keeping a land-force in times of peace, with the dangers that may follow on it</title>
            <author>Somers, John Somers, Baron, 1651-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4642</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11547</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11910555</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11910555</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50801</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60882)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50801)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 514:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter ballancing the necessity of keeping a land-force in times of peace, with the dangers that may follow on it</title>
                  <author>Somers, John Somers, Baron, 1651-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First edition.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  1689-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50801:1"/>
            <p>A LETTER, BALLANCING THE NECESSITY OF KEEPING <hi>A Land-Force</hi> In Times of PEACE: WITH The DANGERS that may follow on it.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1697.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:50801:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50801:2"/>
            <head>A LETTER, BALLANCING THE NECESSITY OF KEEPING <hi>A Land-Force</hi> In Times of PEACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE have at laſt an Honourable Peace, which was much Longed for by us all, but Deſpaired of by many. <hi>England</hi> is now the Wonder of the World; nothing can hurt us, but Animoſities and Jealouſies
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50801:3"/>among our ſelves. If we maintain the Peace with as much Prudence and Judgment, as we have ſhewed Spirit and Courage in carrying on the War, we ſhall give Laws to all about us; and ſecure that Quiet, which we have procured to the reſt of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Means of doing this, is now the common Subject of Diſcourſe. All agree in one Thing, That we ought to maintain our Empire on the Sea with powerful Fleets, ſtrong Summer and Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Guards; and that our Stores ought to be well filled, and our great Ships kept in ſuch a State, that we may be in a condition upon ſhort Warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſet out Royal Fleets. This is ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, that I ſuppoſe it is needleſs to ſpend more time upon it. The only Point in which our Opinions may perhaps differ, is, whether we ought to maintain ſo conſiderable a Force at Land, as will be ſufficient to make a Stand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt an Invaſion; or whether the Militia can be made ſo conſiderable, that we may truſt to it at home, as well as to our Fleets abroad, and be ſafe in this.</p>
            <p>I will not ſuggeſt ſo unbecoming a Thought, as to imagine that any of our Neighbours will ſeek to take Advantages againſt us, or break the Peace, and invade us contrary to the Honour and Faith of Treaties. No, I will not ſuſpect it. But the beſt Guaranty of a Peace, is a good Force to maintain it: And the ſureſt way to keep
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50801:3"/>all our Neighbours to an exact Performance of Articles, is to be upon our Guard. They will be then faithful to Agreements; when they ſee no Opportunities of Surprizing us, and that our Peace does not lay us aſleep, and make us forget the Art of War. I mean, it is no Reflection on any of the Neighbouring Princes, when I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that their Faith is not ſo abſolute a Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but that we muſt help them to be true to their Word, by ſhewing them that they are not like to gain much by breaking it.</p>
            <p>But miſtake me not:</p>
            <p>When I ſeem to prepare you to conſider the Neceſſity of keeping a Land-Force, I am far from the Thought of a <hi>Standing Army.</hi> Any Man who would pretend to give a Jealouſy of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the King, and ſuggeſt that he could not be ſafe among them without he were environ'd with Guards and Troops, as it was in the late Reigns, ought to by abhorred by every true <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh man,</hi> by every Man who loves Liberty, and his Country. The Caſe at preſent is, Whether conſidering the Circumſtances that we and our Neighbours are now in, it may not be both pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and neceſſary for us to keep up a reaſonable Force from Year to Year. The State of Affairs both at Home and Abroad being every Year to be conſidered in Parliament, that ſo any ſuch Force may be either encreaſed, leſſened, or quite laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, as they ſhall ſee cauſe. I will not Argue with you ſo unfairly, as to urge much the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50801:4"/>that we have of Truſting the King; for how much ſoever may be ſaid on this Head, either from his Temper, his Circumſtances, his Intereſt, and the Courſe of his paſt Life, either with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the United Provinces, or to us here in <hi>England,</hi> and with how much Reaſon ſoever this might be proſecuted, yet I will not lay much Weight on it; for it is not juſt to preſs an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that puts another Man in Pain, when he goes to anſwer it: I know it may be ſaid, That Men are but Men; ſo that we make a dangerous Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment of their Virtue, when we put too much in their Power: And that what is done to one King, who deſerves it, and will manage it faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, will be made an Argument to do the ſame for another King, that has neither Merit nor Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to entitle him to ſo entire a Conſidence.</p>
            <p>To ſay all in one Word, if we were in the ſame Condition in which we and our Neighbours were an Age ago, I ſhould reject the Propoſition with Horrour. But the Caſe is altered; the whole World, more particularly our Neighbours, have now got into the miſtaken Notion of keeping up a mighty Force; and the powerfulleſt of all theſe happens to be our next Neighbour, who will very probably keep up great Armies: And we may appear too Inviting, if we are in ſuch an open and unguarded Condition, that the Succeſs of the Attempt may ſeem to be not only proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but certain. <hi>England</hi> is an open Country, full of Plenty, every where able to Subſiſt an
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50801:4"/>Army: Our Towns and Cities are all open; our Rivers are all fordable; no Paſſes nor ſtrong Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces can ſtop an Enemy, that ſhould Land upon us. So that the whole Nation lies open to any Army that ſhould once come into it. To this you may reply, Can an Army be brought toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with a Fleet to bring it over, and we know nothing of it? Theſe Things require time, and we cannot be ſuppoſed ſo deſtitute of Intelligence as not to know of ſuch Preparations. In ſuch a caſe, our Fleet will cover us, while our Militia may be exerciſed, and marched where the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is apprehended. This may ſeem plauſible, and will no doubt work on ſuch as do not conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Things with the Attention that is neceſſary. But do not we remember, that we were lately twice almoſt ſurprized; once from <hi>La Hogue,</hi> and again from <hi>Calais.</hi> We muſt not expect that God will always work Miracles for us, if we are wanting to our ſelves. If in a time of War and Jealouſy we were ſo near the being fatally over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run, without either Warning or Intelligence; it is much more poſſible to ſee ſuch Deſigns laid in a time of Sloth and Quiet, when we are under no Fears nor Apprehenſions: And this may be ſo managed, that the Notice we may have of it, may come too late for us to be able to prevent or reſiſt it. And what will our Intelligence ſignify, if we are in no condition either to hinder the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent, or to withſtand the Force that may be ſent againſt us. Abſolute Governments, where
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50801:5"/>all depends on the Will of the Prince, and where Men are ruined, who fail either in performing what is expected from them, or in keeping the Secreſy that is enjoyned them, can both contrive and execute Things in another manner, than can be conceived by thoſe who have the Happineſs to live in free Governments. Troops may have ſuch Orders for Marches and Countor-marches, that thoſe who are on the Place ſhall not be able to judge what is intended, till it is not poſſible to hinder it. Croſs Winds may make this come yet later, to thoſe who have a Sea between them. Orders may be given to many different Perſons in many different Places, who ſhall know nothing of one another, till they meet in a General Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvous.</p>
            <p>It is true, we muſt ſuppoſe that we ſhall have good Fleets abroad, but one would not put ſo great a thing, as the Safety of the Nation, to ſuch a Hazard, nor depend upon a ſingle Security when that is liable to Accidents. The ſame Wind that may bring over a Fleet, and Army, to invade us, may keep our Ships in Port; ſo that it ſhall not be poſſible for them to look out, or if they ſhould have a favourable Minute to get out, it may ſo ſhatter them that they ſhall not be able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend either our Seas or our Ports. This may well be ſuppoſed, for it really happened when the King landed firſt in <hi>England.</hi> The late King had then a powerful Fleet, which, if it could have engaged the <hi>Dutch,</hi> would have been probably too hard
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50801:5"/>for them, eſpecially conſidering the Tranſport Fleet that they guarded; but the Eaſt Wind, that brought over the King, kept them in the River 'till the <hi>Dutch</hi> had paſt them; and when they got out, a Storm ſtop'd and ſhattered them, ſo that without being able to come to any Action, they were laid up. And would any Man hazard the Nation up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch a Contingency.</p>
            <p>But the laſt thing in reſerve is our <hi>Militia.</hi> Great Bodies may be brought together; The Men are brave, capable of Diſcipline, and they naturally love their Countrey: Their Officers being Men of Eſtates, may be well truſted with the Concerns of the Nation, in which they have ſo good a Stake.</p>
            <p>I will never enter upon ſo invidious an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as to diſparage our <hi>Militia,</hi> or derogate from them: I do not doubt but they are much the beſt in the World, and if they had a Militia to deal with, I ſhould doubt little of the Deciſion. But you and I have ſeen Armies too much not to know the difference that is between Troops that have been long trained, who have learned the Art and are accuſtomed to the Diſcipline of War, and the beſt Bodies of raw and undiſciplined Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes. The whole Method of War is now ſuch, that diſciplined Troops muſt prove a very une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Match, to much greater Numbers of Men, who yet perhaps, upon half their Practice, might prove too hard for them. I know it will be urged, that our Militia may be ſo trained and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delled,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50801:6"/>as to be made more capable of Service then perhaps they are at preſent: This is a Work of Time: a Project that depends upon ſo many Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and may be ſubject to ſo many Slips in the Execution, that it muſt be confeſs'd a Nation is much expoſed, if its Safety and Preſervation muſt depend upon ſuch Uncertainties. We have Troops that have paſs'd through a long Appren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhip, and to our coſt have learned that unhappy Trade, which is now become ſo univerſal, that it is thereby made neceſſary; we muſt either be preſerved by it, or we muſt periſh by it. Many gallant Gentlemen have broke the courſe of their Studies, and the other Methods of Life they were in: It will not only be a hardſhip put upon them, but it will be the rendring our ſelves naked and defenceleſs, if, after all the Reputation that we have riſen to in War, we ſhould ſink into an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becomming Remiſsneſs in Peace, and upon the remote and uncertain Fears of Dangers that will probably never happen, expoſe our ſelves to thoſe which we may certainly look for, as ſoon as we have put our ſelves out of a Capacity of reſiſting them. To tell you Truth, I cannot ſee ſome Men grow all of the ſudden ſuch wonderful Patriots, ſo jealous of the Prerogative, and ſuch Zealots for publick Liberty, without remembring what their Behaviour was, ſome years ago, in the late Reigns; when we had not only all the juſteſt Cauſes of Jealouſie, but all the Certainties of Evidence: The Deſigns were bare-faced, and the Attempts
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50801:6"/>were bold; and yet ſome were then ſilent, and others went into them, with as hearty a Zeal for Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrarineſs as they ſeem now to put on for Liberty. The Methods they have taken during the War have been ſo ill diſguiſed, that few will believe they are in earneſt, when they talk of Liberty and Law, who ſeemed to have laboured hard to lay us open to Invaſion and Conqueſt. What they could not compaſs during the War, they hope now to bring about by laying us aſleep in Peace; for if we let go a real Security, and truſt to an imaginary one, we may pay too dear for the Experiment, and be convinced of our Error when it will be no more in our Power to correct it.</p>
            <p>But I know ſome will urge the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedemonian</hi> States for our Militia. It is a wrong way of arguing, to apply the Precedent of any one Time to another, unleſs all Things in both Times did agree. Every Thing is ſafe in any State, when it is equal, if not ſuperior to thoſe about it. <hi>Lacedemon</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> were at leaſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame foot with their Neighbours. They were indeed far ſuperiour to them: At <hi>Lacedemon</hi> they bred their Youth to nothing but War, or to other Exerciſes that render them fit for it, and to a ſhort and pointed way of Talking. They had neither Arts nor Learning among them: So that their whole Republick was like a Standing Army, that threatned the reſt of <hi>Greece.</hi> The <hi>Romans,</hi> in the Times of their Liberty, were but a little diſtinguiſhed from them. They allowed indeed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:50801:7"/>of Agriculture, and put their own Hands to it, which the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> left to their Slaves: But they were all trained to War; and no Man among them could pretend to Imployments, 'till he could reckon up ſo many Campaigns, and ſhaw the Wounds he had received in them: So that here was a Military Republick. It was not only equal but ſuperior to all about them, for this very thing, and ſo no wonder if it conquered them. Theſe Precedents can never ſuit our Times, unleſs we could change our whole Conſtitution at home, as well as the State of Affairs abroad, and baniſh from us not only Luxury but both Wealth and Trade. The accounts that we have of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia in <hi>Sueden</hi> are not very encouraging: The new modelling it there has ſignified little to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their Liberty.</p>
            <p>Others will perhaps ask, How did our Anceſtors not only defend our Countrey, but render it ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible to all about it, particularly to thoſe from whom we ſeem now to be moſt in danger? This is a Topick that may furniſh a great deal of popular Eloquence, and may impoſe upon ſuch as are proud of the Valour of their Countrey, and have read only ſo much Hiſtory as to remember the Names of ſome Battels, and the Numbers of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. But all were then alike as to this Matter, while all Nations were equally ignorant of War, and were only ſet on the Arts of Peace; then, no doubt, in thoſe ſhort Wars that broke out, the braver Nation had always the better. But it
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50801:7"/>is evident from the firſt Beginnings of Hiſtory down to this day, that Regular Troops were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways too hard for a Militia. <hi>Lacedemon, Athens,</hi> and <hi>Thebes,</hi> in their Turns had the better of one another, as their Armies were better trained, and had more Experience in War. At laſt the King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> who had been much deſpiſed by them, ſubdued them all. <hi>Cyrus,</hi> by training the <hi>Perſians,</hi> conquered the <hi>Babylonians;</hi> and <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> by the Army which his Father had trained, thô he had numerous Armies, or rather a great Militia brought againſt him, yet he made an eaſy as well as a ſpeedy Conqueſt of the <hi>Perſian</hi> Empire. While the <hi>Romans</hi> were but a Militia, thô they were the beſt that ever was, they made War on their Neighbours, who were weaker than they, with great Advantage; but when <hi>Hanniball</hi> came againſt them with a trained Army, they fell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him upon every Occaſion, till a long War had taught them that Art, and then they not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beat him out of <hi>Italy,</hi> but forced <hi>Carthage</hi> to a Submiſſion. Nothing ſtood before the <hi>Roman</hi> Armies, as long as they were kept under Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, but when all the order of War was broke, and they became a Militia, the Northern Nations in <hi>Europe,</hi> as well as the Saracens in the <hi>East,</hi> over-run the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. As the Saracens ſlackened their Diſcipline, the <hi>Turks</hi> carried it from them: And if they had depended on their <hi>Timariots,</hi> and had not truſted more to their <hi>Jani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries</hi> and <hi>Spahi's,</hi> they had not been the Terror
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50801:8"/>of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> for ſo many Ages. So certain it is, from the Hiſtories of all Nations, that regular and diſciplined Troops will be far ſuperior to the beſt and ſtrongeſt Militia in the World.</p>
            <p>To all this it may be ſaid, How did we do in Queen <hi>Eliſabeth</hi>'s Time? Our Militia was then our only Army; to it we truſted, and we were preſerved by it. But I muſt crave leave to put you in mind of ſome Particulars in this part of our Hiſtory: We were then in ſuch imminent Danger, that we were given for gone by the wiſeſt Men of the Age: It was the Storms and Winds, the diſproportioned Bulk of their Ships, the Stiffneſs of the Orders, and the Diſtaſte given to the Prince of <hi>Parma;</hi> all which concurred at that time to ſave <hi>England:</hi> Neither our Militia, nor our Fleet had ſhare in it. There was an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Concurrence of many Things in that juncture that preſerved us: But it were to preſume too much on Providence to lay our ſelves as open as we were then, becauſe we were at that time ſo wonderfully delivered. But I muſt tell you our Danger is now much greater: <hi>Spain,</hi> it is true, had then a great Armada, vaſt Treaſures, and well diſciplined Armies; But tho' their Army lay near us in <hi>Flanders,</hi> the Scene of their Councils, their Fleet and Treaſures were at a great diſtance from us: And yet all the wiſe Men of that time thought we muſt have periſhed then. The Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is now both nearer and greater; a mighty Power, well united, and practiſed in War, and a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50801:8"/>great Naval Force is in view of us. It will be therefore no Argument, becauſe we run a great risk in Q. <hi>Eliſabeth</hi>'s time, but were wonderfully ſaved, that therefore now, when we may be in greater hazard, and have a more formidable Neighbour at our very Doors, we ought to take no care of our ſelves, but neglect the Only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable means of our Prefervation; we have had Two wonderful Eighty Eights, but we preſume too much if we look for a Third, without taking any further Care how, or by what means, we ſhall be ſaved.</p>
            <p>I will add no more on this head, but will only tell you a Saying of one of the <hi>Vere</hi>'s, which is ſtill remembred in the Family. The Queen ſent to the States for thoſe two famous Generals, to command her Army. It ſeemed full of Zeal and Courage: The Queen rid up and down through it, to animate the Soldiers, and was every where anſwered with Shouts and Acclamations: She asked one of the Brothers, what he thought of the Army; he anſwered, It was a brave Army: But ſhe ſaw by his manner that he was in ſome doubt about it, ſo ſhe charged him to explain himſelf; he ſaid, He had not the Name of a Coward in the World, but he was the only Coward there. They were all wiſhing to have the <hi>Spaniards</hi> land, and every Man was telling what Feats he would then do; he was the only Man that was trembling for fear of it.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:50801:9"/>
            <p>The laſt and ſtrongeſt Objection againſt all this is, That this Force will grow upon us, and continue among us: It will have ſuch an Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence within Doors, that it will maintain it ſelf in the H. of Commons; or, if that ſhould fail, it will turn them out of Doors, and quickly find ways to ſubſiſt, to grow upon the Ruins of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Property. This is a large Field; and Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory is ſo full of Inſtances this way, that it will be eaſie to open copiouſly on the ſubject. From the <hi>Pretorian</hi> Cohorts down to our modern Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, enough can be gathered to give a very frightful Repreſentation of a Standing Army. Who doubts it? But all the Rhetorick that this head will afford is wrong applied in this caſe. It is not to be ſuppoſed, but that once a year a Parliament muſt have this matter a freſh under their Conſideration. They will ſee how the State of Affairs varies, either at Home or Abroad; and whether the Forces are brought under ſuch a Management, that there is juſt cauſe of Jealouſy. And I leave it to you to judge, whether it is poſſible in ſo ſhort a time, ſo to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del and influence it, as to prepare them to invade their Country, and to deſtroy our Conſtitution. What <hi>Ceſar,</hi> with all his Genius, could not work his Army to, but after Ten Years Conduct and Succeſs, can give ſmall Encouragement to others to attempt to bring it about, in one Year. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps you are more afraid of a Secret Influence, than of Open Violence from them. The ſhort
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50801:9"/>of this is, You are afraid the Houſe will be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted: I confeſs it is hard to anſwer this, Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſy is ſtubborn and incurable; Melancholy when it grows to be a Diſeaſe, raiſes many ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary Fears; they who are haunted with that ſullen Humour, neither know what they are Afraid of, nor why. Poſſible Accidents are ever before them; and the thinking of theſe perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, ruines their Health, ſours their Humour, and makes them neglect all their preſent and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Concerns, while they are ever dreaming of what will probably never happen. We muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider our preſent Danger, and the likelieſt Ways of ſecuring our ſelves from it, without amuſing our ſelves with what may poſſibly be brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout at ſome diſtance of time. Our Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives do well to ſecure our Conſtitution, by the moſt effectual Means they can think on: But after all, we muſt truſt <hi>England</hi> to a <hi>Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> that is to it ſelf. When ever the fatal Time comes, that this Nation grows weary of Liberty, and has neither the Virtue, the Wiſdom, nor the Force to preſerve its Conſtitution, it will deliver all up; let all the Laws poſſible, and all the Bars imaginable, be put in the way to it. It is no more poſſible to make a Government im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, than it is to make a Man immortal. I do not deny but ſeveral Inconveniences may be apprehended from a Standing Force, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhould not go about to perſwade you to it, if the Thing did not ſeem indiſpenſibly neceſſary
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50801:10"/>to our Preſervation. I would not have us ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon preſent and certain Ruine, becauſe that which muſt preſerve us now from it, may at ſome time hereafter have ill Effects on our Liberty. They cannot be Conſiderable as long as <hi>England</hi> is true to it ſelf; and whenſoever the Nation has loſt that Noble Senſe of Liberty, by which it has been ſo long preſerved, it will ſoon make Letters for it ſelf, thô it ſhould find none at hand ready made.</p>
            <p>To conclude, This Matter is of ſo nice, and yet of ſo important a Nature, that it ought to be ſeverely examined, without falſe Colours, or popular Rhetorick; you know me to be ſo jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of Liberty, to have been always ſo true to it, to have ventured ſo much for it, and to have ſuch a Stake in it, that you cannot ſuſpect me. You know that I neither have, nor can have any Views in this Matter, but at our preſent Safety, as well as the Continuance of our Conſtitution and Liberty for the future.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50801:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
